hey folks right here let's talk about
the evolutionary purpose of life this is
actually a fairly easy question though
the answer has very disturbing
implications behind me you'll see
foxglove which is an invasive species
here in the Pacific Northwest
it's digitalis which is the source of a
very important cardiac drug you probably
also see some bees that are pollinating
it and no doubt you'll see some
mosquitoes flying around me truth is
that all of these creatures and human
beings have the same purpose because
evolutionarily there can be only one the
purpose of living creatures is to
advance the spelling's that they find
within their genomes into the future now
we could say it's that produce as many
copies as possible in the next
generation that's not quite right though
it works as a proxy for most things but
we can say that genomes are agreements
between genes of different loci to
advance the interests of all of the
spellings found there to the exclusion
of alternative spellings that might be
found in other members of the same
species and what does it mean that
mosquitoes and bees and plants and
humans all share this purpose it means
that the purpose isn't very interesting
it's generic what is interesting is the
different evolutionary machinery that we
have all inherited with which to advance
our spellings now my argument would be
there is actually one possible exception
one way in which a creature can have a
different purpose but it requires us to
assign that new purpose to ourselves and
step away from the evolutionary
imperative that has guided us for three
and a half billion years yes three and a
half billion years is a good number
it may not be precise but that is the
period of time in which the tree of life
has existed on earth and that means that
you as a member of human species at the
tip of the human branch have an unbroken
line of successful reproduction
stretching back all the way the first
living creature that's an amazing
winning streak it is almost certain to
come to an end for you and me and the
other creatures you see in this frame
within the next few generations most
creatures do not make it
and this bottlenecking effect this
limiting of those creatures who succeed
in reproducing within any cohort to a
very small fraction of the total number
of creatures attempting to do so it is
that bottlenecking
that makes adaptive evolution happen it
reduces the total evolutionary output to
only that small fraction that is very
well suited and also very lucky and able
to continue one more generation into the
future I hope this has been enlightening
and I look forward to talking more about
the implications of the evolutionary
purpose of life in a future video
[Music]